Inventory to the Addition to the Papers of Hardy Cross Dillard 1931-1984
University of Virginia, Arthur J. Morris Law Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Law Library
Addition to the Papers of Hardy Cross Dillard 1931-1984
Special Collections, University of Virginia Law Library
MSS 84-8i
This addition consists of 8 boxes.
Administrative Information
Access
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This addition was given to the Law Library by Hardy Cross Dillard's widow, Valgerdur Dillard, in the spring of 1996.
Scope and Content Information
This addition to the Papers of Hardy Cross Dillard contains miscellaneous subject files, most notably a folder documenting Dillard's views on school segregation. There are also correspondence files, including letters of condolence Mrs. Dillard received after Hardy's death in 1982. In addition there are diplomas, awards and decorations, as well as over 40 photographs. These materials are followed by three boxes of Dillard's published materials.
Contents List
- Argentina-Chile Arbitration Trip 1976 (Box 94)
  Memorabilia
- Army. Virginia Military District 1949-1962 (Box 94)
  Extracts, memos, correspondence
- China 1966 (Box 94)
  Notes and articles
- Commission on Education 1956, 1959 (Box 94)
  Correspondence, memos concerning school segregation in Virginia
- Correspondence 1931-1977, 2 folders (Box 94)
- Correspondence 1956, 1973-1977, 4 folders (Box 95)
- Correspondence with John Wheeler-Bennett 1928-1972 (Box 95)
- Farmer. Status and Pay of Law Librarian 1961 (Box 95)
  Memos, correspondence
- First Year Law Class 1973 (Box 95)
  Notes
- Germany Trip. Orders, Health Certificate, Powers of Attorney 1950 (Box 95)
- Indus River Basin Waters Dispute 1960 (Box 95)
- Humor II [Personal Notes for Talks] n.d. (Box 95)
- International Court of Justice Drafts and Notes ca. 1977 (Box 96)
- International Court of Justice Information Bulletin 1977 (Box 96)
- Letter Informing of His Election as a Member, Signed by U Thant 1969 (Box 96)
- International Peace Academy 1977 (Box 96)
- Jurisprudence: Miscellaneous 1969 (Box 96)
- Letters of Condolence at HCD's Death 1982-1984, 2 folders (Box 96)
- Letters of Sympathy for James Hardy Dillard's Death 1940 (Box 96)
- Library of Congress 1977 (Box 96)
- Libyia/Tunis. Court Shelf Data 1977 (Box 97)
- Manley O. Hudson Medal for Distinguished Scholarship and Achievement in International Law 1982 (Box 97)
- Memorabilia 1966-1981, 3 folders (Box 97)
- Miscellaneous Correspondence 1966-1983 (Box 97)
- Miscellaneous Papers 1971-1982 (Box 97)
- "Montebello." A House Near the University of Virginia 1966 (Box 97)
- National War College 1949-1956 (Box 97)
  Presentations and speeches
- Notes on Rabelais n.d. (Box 97)
- Personal Financial Notes 1980 (Box 97)
- Personal Military Correspondence 1946, 1948, 1962 (Box 97)
- Personal Military Papers ca. 1944-1946? (Box 97)
- Private Preference Article 1958, 1963 (Box 97)
- Speeches 1957, 1963, 1968-1969 (Box 97)
- USMA West Point Questionnaire 1957 (Box 97)
- Washington College Honorary Degree of Doctor of Laws 1976 (Box 97)
- Course Materials:
  - HCD and Mallet, "Introduction to Legal Philosophy" n.d., 1948, 1952, 1953, 1957 (Box 98)
  - HCD, "International Law and Foreign Policy" n.d., 1948, 1950, 1951, 1954, 1959-60 (Box 98)
  - HCD, "International Law" 1947 (Box 98)
  - HCD, "Jurisprudence-Partial Inventory of Recent Books" n.d. (Box 98)
- Diplomas (Box 99)
  - United States Military Academy B.A. Degree June 24, 1924
  - Legal Fraternity of PHI DELTA PHI Initiation into the Minor Inn November 1925
  - University of Virginia Bachelor of Laws June 1927
  - Virginia Board of Examiners July 1927
  - The American Law Institute in recognition as a Member since 1956 (Box 99)
  - Wisdom Award of Honor November 1957 (Box 99)
  - The Great Navy of the State of Nebraska December 1958
  - Honorary Member of the Bar Association of the City of Richmond April 1970 (Box 99)
  - Washington College Doctor Honoris Causa 1976
  - Commonwealth of Virginia as a Member of the Commission on Constitutional Revision [ca. 1970]
  - Academia Mundi Scientiis et Litteris Dedita 1975
  - The American Academy of International Law. The Manley O. Hudson Medal. 1982 (Box 99)
- 14 Medals and Decorations: (Box 99)
  - Omnia Reliquit Servare Rempublican (Box 99)
  - IMP [Secret Society] (Box 99)
  - Raven Society (Box 99)
  - ODK (UVA, 1926) (Box 99)
  - PBK (Box 99)
  - Exceptional Service to the Department of the Air Force (Box 99)
  - Eagle pin [Air Force?] (Box 99)
  - Heroic or Meritorious Achievement (Box 99)
  - USA Medal (Box 99)
  - Various military buttons, pins, and stripes (Box 99)
  - I.D. Tag (Box 99)
- Published Material: (Box 99-101)
  - A Tribute to Philip C. Jessup and Some Comments on International Adjudication, 62 Columbia L. Rev. 1138, 1146 (1962) (Box 99-101)
  - CLE Around the Country. A Quasi-Charismatic Proposal, 15 The Practical Lawyer (1969) (Box 99-101)
  - Commentary, XXI University of Miami L. Rev. 532, 535 (Box 99-101)
  - Conflict and Change: The Role of the Law, Proceedings of the American Society of International Law, 50, 67 (1963) (Box 99-101)
  - Conflict and Persuasion, 29 The Virginia Quarterly Review 351, 368 (1953) (Box 99-101)
  - Diplomacy and the National Interest, 28 The Virginia Quarterly Review, 156, 160 (1952) (Box 99-101)
  - Foreign Policy: Difficulties and Dilemmas, 141, 147 (1955) (Box 99-101)
  - Foreword. A Tribute to Charles O. Gregory, 53 Virginia L. Rev. 759, 762 (1967) (Box 99-101)
  - Freedom of Choice and Democratic Values, 38, The Virginia Quarterly Review, 411, 434 (1962) (Box 99-101)
  - Good Talk and Great Friendship, 17 The Virginia Quarterly Review 471, 473 (1941) (Box 99-101)
  - Herbert Wechsler, 78 Columbia L. Rev. 953, 956 (Box 99-101)
  - In Memoriam: Felix Frankfurter Preliminary Remarks, 51 Virginia L. Rev. 547 (1965) (Box 99-101)
  - Law and Conflict: Some Current Dilemmas, XXIV, Washington and Lee L. Rev. 177, 202 (1967) (Box 99-101)
  - Law and Learning, 47 Virginia L. Rev. 647, 659 (1963) (Box 99-101)
  - Law, Policy and the World Court-Attacking Some Misconceptions, 17 Willamette L. Rev. 13, 25 (1980) (Box 99-101)
  - Major Problems of United States Foreign Policy, 1948-1949--A Study Guide, XXXIX, American Economic Review 800, 802 (1949) (Box 99-101)
  - Minds and Moods, 43 Virginia Quarterly Review 51, 60 (1967) (Box 99-101)
  - Myres S. McDougal. Profound Scholar, Creative Innovator, Genial Humanist, 1 The Denver Journal of International Law and Policy 9, 12 (1971) (Box 99-101)
  - Nationalism: Midcentury Puzzle, 28 The Virginia Quarterly Review 532, 546 (1952) (Box 99-101)
  - Product Liability: Directions for Use and the Duty to Warn, 41 Virginia L. Rev. 145, 182 (1955) (Box 99-101)
  - Reports on Regional Meetings: American Points of View and Practice. Summary and Report, American Society of International Law, 1966 (Box 99-101)
  - Should the Constitution be Amended to Limit the Treaty-Making Power?, 26 California L. Rev. 373, 385 (Box 99-101)
  - Status of South-West Africa (Namibia)-A Separate Opinion, 6, The International Lawyer, 409, 427 (1972) (Box 99-101)
  - Symposium-The Constitution and the Use of Military Force Abroad. Introduction, 10 Virginia Journal of International Law, 32, 36 (1969) (Box 99-101)
  - The Comic Spirit and the Cold War, [Address] The West Virginia Bar Association 74th Meeting, 1958 (Box 99-101)
  - The Policy Oriented Approach to Law, 40 The Virginia Quarterly Review 626, 632 (1964) (Box 99-101)
  - The United States and China: The Problem of Recognition, The Yale Review. A National Quarterly, Winter 1955. (Box 99-101)
  - The University of Virginia School of Law, Virginia Army Game, 1954 (Box 99-101)
  - The World Court-An Inside View, [Address] Proceedings of The American Society of International Law, 1973 (Box 99-101)
  - The World Court-Reflections of a Professor Turned Judge, 27 The American University L. Rev. 205, 250 (1978) (Box 99-101)
  - Two Liberal Justices, 16 The Virginia Quarterly Review 466, 469 (1940) (Box 99-101)
  - Western Germany and the West, 27 The Virginia Quarterly Review 334, 351 (1951) (Box 99-101)
- Rules for Judicial Conduct. Things Necessary to be Continually had in Remembrance by Sir Matthew Hale, Kt
- Photographs
  - Advisory Committee on Foreign Relations of the United States 11/1/1968
  - Air Force Special Advisory Committee [ca. 1960-1970?]
  - Class of '27 in 1952 [?]
  - Class of '27 in [1970s?]
  - Commission on Constitutional Revision Jan. 1969
  - Dillard Family ca. 1905-1908
  - HCD ca. 1920's
  - HCD as a cadet at the U.S. Military Academy 1920-1924
  - HCD ca. late 1970s or early 1980s
  - HCD and A. J. G. Priest October 20, 1954
  - HCD, Photo and Proof Sheets ca. late 1970s
  - HCD at Beagle Channel 1976
  - HCD at Department of State [with group of people]. 11/7/1969
  - HCD, Judge at World Court ca. 1970s
  - HCD speaking ca. 1950
  - HCD at play ca. 1952
  - HCD at Prestwick, Scotland Oct. 1944
  - HCD at The Parthenon ca. 1940s
  - HCD, Honorary Degree at Washington College n.d.
  - HCD in Egypt 1962
  - HCD, Miscellaneous Military Photographs n.d.
  - HCD's Quotations in Charlottesville Court House
  - HCD's Virginia Trial Lawyers Association Distinguished Service Award 1980
  - HCD with Bessie when he was born ca. 1903
  - HCD with his grandchildren in Amsterdam n.d.
  - HCD with military officers [1950s]
  - HCD with unidentified military officers [1950s?]
  - HCD with son and friends in the Lido, Paris ca. 1970-1971
  - HCD with wife Val and Frances Farmer 1978
  - Dillards and Burgers at the Peace Palace, The Hague 1970s
  - Dillard, James Hardy ca. 1930s
  - Gruenther, Alfred M. [National War College] 1946
  - Hill, Harry W. [National War College, V. Adm. US Army] ca. 1946
  - International Court of Justice [ca. 1969-1970s]
  - International Court of Justice. [Two different occasions]
  - JAG School Occasions ca. 1953-1955?
  - Law Day 1963
  - Law Day 1965
  - [School of Military Government] During World War II?, 2 photographs
  - USAWC Eight Annual National Strategy Seminar 6/5-8/1962